<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[<insert witty blog title>]]></title>
  <link href="http://stevendick.github.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://stevendick.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-02-05T16:17:58+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://stevendick.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Steven Dick]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Gradle + Groovy + Spock + Windows == argh!]]></title>
    <link href="http://stevendick.github.com/blog/2012/02/05/gradle-plus-groovy-plus-spock-plus-windows-equals-equals-argh-slash/"/>
    <updated>2012-02-05T14:29:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://stevendick.github.com/blog/2012/02/05/gradle-plus-groovy-plus-spock-plus-windows-equals-equals-argh-slash</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We&#8217;ve all experienced the &#8216;pleasure&#8217; of <a href="http://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/yak_shaving">Yak shaving</a>. This is the tale of my most recent one.</p>

<p>In porting our build to <a href="http://www.gradle.org">Gradle</a> we recently found we&#8217;d missed one project as part of the multi-project build. Easy, we just add the project to Gradles <code>settings.gradle</code> and all will be well.</p>

<p>Nope.</p>

<p>Another project in the build fails and it has no obvious relation to the newly re-added project. WTF? Some error about <code>groovyc</code> (the Ant task for building Groovy code) has failed.</p>

<p>A bit of googling shows we&#8217;ve run up against the command line limitation on Windows (8K for XP onwards, only 2K for older versions). Bummer, but we can change the default Gradle behaviour to run the Groovy compilation in-process rather than spawning the compiler from the command line and encountering the problem.</p>

<p>That should work. Nope.</p>

<p>Now <a href="https://github.com/spockframework/spock">Spock</a> is complaining that we&#8217;ve failed to process the annotations on all tests using Spock. This must be because we&#8217;re running in-process and Spock&#8217;s annotation processor isn&#8217;t on the classpath.</p>

<p>Maybe adding Spock to Gradle&#8217;s classpath fixes this new problem? Nope.</p>

<p>OK, back to googling around. <a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/5434482/how-can-i-create-a-pathing-jar-in-gradle">Stack Overflow</a> shows a workaround for problems of classpaths that are too long. Basically, replace the long classpath with an empty JAR containing a MANIFEST.MF that defines the real classpath. Sounds easy enough.</p>

<p>Does the pathing JAR solve the problem? Nope. The first problem with this solution is the lack of a clear description with examples of how this works. The classpath. The paths should be relative URLs (absolute paths appear to work on Mac OS X, but not Windows) from the point-of-view of the pathing JAR. I did this, but none of my classpath dependencies were found and no obvious reason why.</p>

<p>Argh! Back to Google. I eventually found a recent <a href="http://jira.codehaus.org/browse/GROOVY-5024">bug</a> about the command line length problem with Groovy and a proposed patch (not yet accepted). I also raised a problem with the Gradle guys to see if anyone else could point out a workaround.</p>

<p>After giving it a day and no simple workaround appearing, I decided to try and apply the patch myself and build my own local Groovy. I used the 1.8.5 version of Groovy and manually applied the patch in Eclipse as the patch line numbers didn&#8217;t match up to the source. Groovy recently moved to building with Gradle, so after cleaning up the <code>docs.gradle</code> file (it had diff markings in it, meaning it didn&#8217;t work), I was able to build with Gradle. The build did report an error right at the end, but this was after the<code>groovy</code> and <code>groovy-all</code> JARs were produced, so that wasn&#8217;t a problem.</p>

<p>Using the locally built Groovy did have one downside: I needed to provide the needed dependencies explicitly rather than relying on the transitive dependencies automatically being resolved, but that&#8217;s a small price to pay.</p>

<p>So at last, the build works and I can leave that particular Yak alone.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[JaCoCo &amp; Gradle]]></title>
    <link href="http://stevendick.github.com/blog/2012/01/22/jacoco-and-gradle/"/>
    <updated>2012-01-22T18:01:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://stevendick.github.com/blog/2012/01/22/jacoco-and-gradle</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There&#8217;s a new kid on the block when it comes to code coverage in the Java world: <a href="http://http://www.eclemma.org/jacoco/">JaCoCo</a> (Java Code Coverage).</p>

<p>It comes from the guys who did the EclEmma plug-in for Eclipse after they decided it wasn&#8217;t worthwhile to evolve the Emma code coverage tool (they are not the original developers). Instead they decided to start over and JaCoCo is the (ongoing) result.</p>

<p>We originally used Emma for the code coverage, but this stopped working when we started using <a href="http://http://www.eclemma.org/jacoco/">Lombok</a> to generate all the boilerplate code that Java needs. The next step was Cobertura. I&#8217;ve worked with Cobertura in the past and found the build integration brittle; you end up with either 0% or 100% coverage and no obvious errors. Luckily one of the other guys set Cobertura up with our Ant build so I didn&#8217;t need to do it again.</p>

<p>Now I&#8217;m moving our build over to <a href="http://projectlombok.org/">Gradle</a> and wanted to look at how JaCoCo was progressing. I was pleasently surprised to find they&#8217;ve released, so I went looking for documentation on how to get this working with Gradle. No such luck and no-one to my knowledge has (yet) written a Gradle plug-in. After this, maybe I will.</p>

<p>JaCoCo does ship with Ant tasks and since Gradle includes Ant, it is very easy to use the tasks to get the work done.</p>

<p>My first problem was working out where to get JaCoCo. Maven Central seemed the logical source, but that version appeared to be missing the Ant task and wouldn&#8217;t work with my Gradle script. I went for downloading JaCoCo and adding the Jar to my build project to solve the problem.</p>

<p>One difference with JaCoCo from Cobertura is it uses a Java agent to instrument the classes on loading; no longer do we need to post-compile instrument the class files. This seems a much cleaner way of doing things.</p>

<p>A quick bit of googling turned up the solution for specifying the agent argument when executing our tests in the Gradle build:</p>

<div><script src='https://gist.github.com/1657770.js?file=junit.groovy'></script>
<noscript><pre><code>dependencies {
  codeCoverage files(&quot;${rootProject.projectDir.path}/lib/jacocoagent.jar&quot;)
}
 
test {
  jvmArgs &quot;-javaagent:${configurations.codeCoverage.singleFile}=destfile=${buildDirName}/coverage-results/jacoco.exec,sessionid=HSServ,append=false&quot;,
    'Djacoco=true',
    '-Xms128m',
    '-Xmx512m',
    '-XX:MaxPermSize=128m'
}</code></pre></noscript></div>


<p>The first thing I do is add the JaCoCo jar to a new Gradle configuration, codeCoverage. This allows me to keep the JaCoCo Jar seperate from other compile and test dependencies.</p>

<p>I&#8217;m passing a number of arguments to the agent to control JaCoCo&#8217;s behaviour:</p>

<ol>
<li><code>${configurations.codeCoverage.singleFile}</code></li>
<li><code>destfile=${buildDirName}/coverage-results/jacoco.exec</code></li>
<li><code>sessionid=HSServ</code></li>
<li><code>append=false</code></li>
</ol>


<p>Taking each of these lines in turn, we have:</p>

<ol>
<li><p>Here I make use a new configuration, <code>codeCoverage</code>, to resolve the location of the JaCoCo Jar file.</p></li>
<li><p>JaCoCo writes the code coverage metrics to a binary file we specify here.</p></li>
<li><p>Identify the code coverage session. I haven&#8217;t had any success in seeing this in the results.</p></li>
<li><p>Re-create the output file each time rather than appending to an existing file.</p></li>
</ol>


<p>This is enough to generate the statistics, but it doesn&#8217;t generate the report. For the report you need to do more work:</p>

<div><script src='https://gist.github.com/1657770.js?file=generate-coverage-report.groovy'></script>
<noscript><pre><code>task generateCoverageReport &lt;&lt; {
  ant {
    taskdef(name:'jacocoreport', classname: 'org.jacoco.ant.ReportTask') {
      classpath path: &quot;${rootProject.projectDir.path}/lib/jacocoant.jar&quot;
    }
       
    mkdir dir: &quot;${buildDirName}/reports/coverage&quot;
       
    jacocoreport {
      executiondata {
        fileset(dir: &quot;${buildDirName}/coverage-results&quot;) {
          ant.file file: 'jacoco.exec'
        }
      }
           
      structure(name: project.name) {
               
        classfiles {
          fileset dir: &quot;${project.buildDir.path}/classes/main&quot;
        }
        
        // this is for Windows
        sourcefiles(encoding: 'CP1252') {
          fileset dir: &quot;${project.projectDir.path}/src/main/java&quot;
        }
      }
           
      xml  destfile: &quot;${buildDirName}/reports/coverage/jacoco.xml&quot;
      html destdir: &quot;${buildDirName}/reports/coverage&quot;
    }
  }
}</code></pre></noscript></div>


<p>Phew! There&#8217;s a lot going on here. This is where we make use of the Ant tasks that come with JaCoCo. Let&#8217;s break it down a bit:</p>

<h3>lines 3 - 5</h3>

<p>Define an Ant task for the JaCoCo reporting task.</p>

<h3>line 7</h3>

<p>The output directory needs to exist before the report is run.</p>

<h3>lines 10 - 14</h3>

<p>Point JaCoCo to the binary file generated from the test run.</p>

<h3>lines 16 - 26</h3>

<p>The JaCoCo report needs access to the class and source files.</p>

<h3>line 28</h3>

<p>Create an XML output file (this isn&#8217;t needed if you&#8217;re only interested in the HTML output).</p>

<h3>line 29</h3>

<p>Create HTML report.</p>

<p>I link the HTML output in our <a href="http://jenkins-ci.org">Jenkins</a> build (I&#8217;m not aware of a Jenkins plug-in for JaCoCo yet).</p>

<p>The Gradle build where I use JaCoCo is a multi-project build which gives us the added challenge of combining the results from each project into a single report, but that&#8217;s for another blog entry&#8230;</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
